Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2013 and undated RL.00219
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Sheep Ranching in Montana, 2004-2005, 2013, 2 boxes; 97 prints
  - Pachy Burns in the tent where "Jam to Lamb" participants slept/ate. Louise Swartzwalder (at left). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 11)
  - Pachy Burns in the tent where "Jam to Lamb" participants slept/ate. Louise Swartzwalder (at left). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 12)
  - Pachy Burns in the tent where "Jam to Lamb" participants slept/ate. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 13)
  - Denise R. Gentsch tending to sickly lamb. She and her husband, Bryan, were "Jam to Lamb" particpants in the Spring of 2004. Greenough, Montana. (Box 28, Image 14)
  - Fran Woody showing digitized images of sheep to me from her computer. Bryan Gentsch's back facing the camera. We were in the tent set up to accomodate "Jam to Lamb" participants. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 15)
  - Bryan Gentsch, Louise Swartzwalder (standing), Fran Woody, with computer, Felice Austin and Pachy Burns. 2004 "Jam to Lamb," Greenough, Montana. (Box 28, Image 16)
  - Sheep on the run--The property at "Paws Up" Ranch--leased to Pachy Burns, Greenough, Montana--Spring 2004. (Box 28, Image 17)
  - Just outside our tent--cooking lamb sausage for dinner. 2004 "Jam to Lamb" event, Greenough, Montana (Box 28, Image 18)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano Jr. and Sr. feeding "bums" (lambs who were rejected by their mothers). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 19)
  - Pachy Burns (left) and Bryan Gentsch (far right) attend to wheel problems on Pachy's Airstream trailer. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. Bryan is from Austin, Texas. He and Pachy met at an agricultural conference years earlier. (Box 28, Image 20)
  - Linda Brunckhorst holding a lamb. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. Linda was a long-time friend of Pachy's and would often show up to help. (Box 28, Image 21)
  - Linda Brunckhorst, a friend of Pachy Burns... Pachy's vintage Airstream trailer and "Jam to Lamb" tent. The buildings belonged to "Paws Up" Ranch, from which Pachy had a lease. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 22)
  - Pachy Burns and Linda Brunckhorst numbering lambs with red or blue (harmless) ink. Pachy had an elaborate system of keeping track of births and bloodlines that was unusual for raising sheep. She kept a LARGE book of hand-written records everybody called "The Bible." Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (I love the earrings!) (Box 28, Image 23)
  - My niece, Felice Austin, with newly "branded" lamb--(harmless ink). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Felice is the oldest of four children of my sister, Nancy Jane Austin, who passed in 1989. Felice was 12 at the time.) (Box 28, Image 24)
  - Pachy Burns (left), Denise Rhodes Gentsch (center) and Linda Brunckhorst getting ready to doctor a lamb. The little medical kit was created by Jennifer Nelson, a previous "Jam to Lamb" participant and friend of Piney Hardiman--Pachy's oldest daughter. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 25)
  - Denise R. Gentsch (left) and Linda Brunckhorst working on a lamb's infected umbilical cord. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 26)
  - Esteban Lozano, Jr. balancing on the "jugs" (a term used to describe the small, wooden pens made to holds ewes/lambs). Esteban was working for Pachy in order to save money to finish dental school in Peru. (Box 28, Image 27)
  - My niece, Felice Austin, sewing Pachy Burns' torn jacket. Inside Pachy's vintage Airstream trailer. Near Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 28)
  - Inside Pachy Burns' vintage Airstream trailer. The small picture of a man on a horse (about center) is of her husband, Horatio "Rasch" Burns--a successful cattle rancher in Big Timber, Montana. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 29)
  - My niece, Felice Austin, feeding a sick lamb in the middle of the night. The lamb died sometime the next morning, and Felice was devastated. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 30)
  - Pachy Burns reviewing notes. Losing lambs was something Pachy took very seriously. She leased from "Paws Up" Ranch, hence the large out buildings. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 31)
  - Judith Faye "Pachy" Burns with lamb. Greenough, Montana--2004 (May). (Box 28, Image 32)
  - Pachy Burns with sickly lamb. Greenough, Montana, 2004 "Jam to Lamb" in springtime. (Box 28, Image 33)
  - Pachy Burns (left) and Denise R. Gentsch (from Austin, TX) feeding "bums"--lambs rejected by their mothers. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 34)
  - Bryan and Denise Gentsch built this feeding station to accomodate "bums"--lambs rejected by their mothers. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 35)
  - Bryan and Denise Gentsch in the tent shared with "Jam to Lamb" participants. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 36)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano Jr. and Sr. out on the range with sheep. Photograph made with 35mm panoramic camera. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 37)
  - Mother ewe and lambs, just outside their "jug" or pen. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. The lamb at the bottom of photograph was born just that hour. (Box 28, Image 38)
  - Remains of sheep who died for various reasons. About 50 yards from the camp/tent/buildings. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 39)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. out walking--about 200 yards from the camp for "Jam to Lamb" participants. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 40)
  - I don't remember the reason why this lamb, several weeks old, was strung up. I want to say it was cooked for dinner that evening, but I can't be certain. Maybe it was butchered and given to somebody. Greenough, Montana, "Paws Up" Ranch building, Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 41)
  - Strung up lamb. Bryan Gentsch beheaded it, and I believe he skinned it as well. "Paws Up" Ranch building (property that was leased to Pachy Burns for her "Jam to Lamb" events and for summer grazing), Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 42)
  - My niece, Felice Austin (left), Pachy Burns (center) and Linda J. Brunckhorst (from Big Timber, Montana) in the tent used for "Jam to Lamb" participants. Pachy had lots of reading material pertaining to sheep and also agriculture in general. She was a natural and gifted teacher. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 43)
  - Pachy Burns involved in a difficult birth. The lamb died during the process. Greenough, Montana, "Jam to Lamb"--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 44)
  - Pachy Burns preparing to remove the skin of a stillborn lamb, afterwhich she will place the skin on a live lamb in order for it to bond to the mother ewe (who produced the stillborn) with the hopes of bonding the "bum" lamb (rejected by its mother) to a new mother ewe. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 45)
    The second of six photographs in the series.
  - Pachy Burns preparing to skin a stillborn lamb (see previous image). Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb" event. (Box 28, Image 46)
    The third in a series of six photographs.
  - Pachy Burns removing the skin of a stillborn lamb. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 47)
    Number four in a series of six photographs.
  - Denise R. Gentsch (left) and Pachy Burns with newly grafted lamb. They are planning to put this "bum" lamb with a mother ewe that gave a stillbirth (the stillborn lamb's skin is on the "bum" lamb). Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 48)
    Number five in a series of six photographs.
  - Bryan Gentsch and Pachy Burns dressing a "bum" lamb (rejected by its mother) with the skin of a lamb who died at birth or shortly after. The bum lamb will be put in a pen with the mother ewe who lost the stillborn, and hopefully the two will bond. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 49)
  - Mother ewe bonding with a "bum" lamb who has been dressed with the skin taken from the stillborn lamb (of this mother ewe). This method does not always work, but this time it did. The mother bonded with her "new" lamb. The skin will be removed in 3 or 4 days. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb" event. (Box 28, Image 50)
    This is the number six photograph in a series of six.
  - Pachy Burns with a skin that had been on a "bum" lamb after it was successfully grafted to a new mother (who lost her own stillborn lamb from which the skin was taken). Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb" event. (Box 28, Image 51)
  - Herd of sheep just before being shorn. On the property of Paws Up Ranch (leased to Pachy Burns), Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 52)
  - Dan Ward getting ready to shear sheep. On the property of Paws Up Ranch (leased to Pachy Burns). Dan is inside the custom-built mobile unit made specifically to shear sheep. He is pulling on custom, handmade footwear he uses while shearing. Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 53)
  - Dan Ward in the mobile sheep-shearing unit. Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 54)
  - Dan Ward in the mobile sheep-shearing unit/trailer. Paws Up Ranch (leased to Pachy Burns) near Greenough, Montana, Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 55)
  - Dan Ward shearing sheep inside the mobile sheep-shearing unit/trailer. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 56)
  - The mobile unit used to shear sheep, on the property of Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana. The sheep would climb the ramp on the left, go inside and get sheared, then he let out doors on the (right) side of the trailer. Rufo Lozano is center. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 57)
  - Michael H. Peters stretching for a few minutes before he begins to shear sheep. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 58)
  - Will Tusick shearing sheep in a mobile unit, on the property of Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 59)
  - Will Tusick shearing sheep in a mobile shearing trailer, Greenough, Montana. Will was very articulate about sheep shearing, and he shared in great detail the proper ways to stand, how to shear quickly and easily. He was adamant about doing the best job without hurting the sheep in any way. Spring 2005. (Box 29, Image 60)
  - Apparatus used for shearing sheep--inside the mobile sheep-shearing unit owned by Keith and Cyndee Braeten, on the property of Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 61)
  - Bluesette Campbell, Pachy Burns' youngest daughter, helping with newly sheared wool. She and her sister, Piney Hardiman, were visiting their mother briefly at the time. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 62)
  - The front end of the mobile sheep-shearing unit/trailer. From left to right (standing): Cyndee Braeten, Bluesette Campbell, Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr.. Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 63)
  - Judith Faye "Pachy" Burns with an armload of newly sheared sheep wool. Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 64)
  - Sorting and sifting newly sheared wool. This rig was made from PVC tubing and served to do a quick cleaning of the wool. Pachy Burns is on the far right. Paws Up Ranch property, near Greenough, Montana. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 65)
  - Kess Kintla Nelson, daughter of Jenn Nelson, and Pachy Burns at play on shearing day. Jenn Nelson met Piney Hardiman, Pachy's oldest daughter, while they were both in college. Jenn participated in some of the early "Jam to Lamb" events back in the early 1990s. Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 66)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. (left corner) and Pachy Burns packing wool in large sacks. Rufo Lozano at top. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 67)
  - Near the day's end... after several hundred sheep had been sheared. I counted 18 bundles at the time, with more to come. Paws Up Ranch property, near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 68)
  - Sheep shearing crew, on the property of Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. From left to right: Dan Ward, Elliston, Montanan--Will Tusick, Polson, Montana--Cyndee and Keith Braeten, Stanford, Montana--Jason Braeten, Kalispell, Montana--Michael H. Peters, Belfry, Montana. (Box 29, Image 69)
  - Running sheep, photograph made with a plastic Holga Camera (and only advancing the film part way to reach exposure). Neary Greenough, Montana--across the road and up a few miles from where "Jam to Lamb" was held the previous spring (2004). Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 70)
  - Running lambs, photograph made with a plastic Holga Camera. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 71)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr., pouring coffee for me in his small camper trailer, a few miles south of the base camp for Pachy Burns' operation. Near Greenough, Montana. He invited us to come to Peru, where he is from and lives for a few months out of the year. I began to make plans, but it never happened... which I truly regret. (Box 29, Image 72)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. walking with his dogs and herding sheep. A few hundred yards from his camper, and a few miles south of the base camp. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 73)
  - The camper where Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. stayed during the night. A few miles south of the base camp, near Greenough, Montana. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 74)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. baking potatoes in his camper oven--The next image was made at the base camp the following morning; of his sons, Esteban, Jr. and Rufo. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 75)
    Two negatives printed consecutively (one in the evening, the next in the morning).
  - Rufo Lozano, the youngest son of Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. walking with dead lamb. A few miles from Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 76)
  - Recently sheared sheep near the base camp constructed by the Lozano brothers and their father. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 77)
  - Rufo Lozano, youngest son of Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr., feeding "bum" lambs (rejected for unknown reasons by their birth mothers). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. His back is resting on a very old log structure that happened to be on the property leased to Pachy Burns. (Box 29, Image 78)
  - Pachy Burns taking off her own jacket and offering it to Ricky Lozano, who had just arrived from Peru. A few miles north of Greenough, Montana. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 79)
  - Esteban Jr., his father (right) and brother (left) sorting sheep shortly after shearing. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 80)
  - A day or two after the sheep had been sheared. From left to right: Esteban, Jr., Rufo, Ricky and Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. on the property of "Paws Up" Ranch (where the sheep shearing took place). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 81)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr. walking sheep that had been recently sheared. "Paws Up" Ranch (leased to Pachy Burns), Greenough, Montana. Esteban Jr., Sr. and others from Peru were introduced to Pachy by way of an agricultural service in Wyoming. (Box 29, Image 82)
  - Lining up sheep in a long chute soon after they have been sheared and administering medicine for de-worming. On the property of Paws Up Ranch, Greenough, Montana. Spring, 2005. (The tube was slipped into their mouths, then injected.) (Box 29, Image 83)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Jr., tending to a sick ewe and her dead (or dying) lamb. Early morning fog above the base camp--this was the morning of my last day of my visit in the Spring of 2005. A few miles north of Greenough, Montana. (Rufo Lozano is pushing the hay cart in the distance.) (Box 29, Image 84)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr., with his all-terrain vehicle and sheep dogs--just arriving at the base camp, near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 85)
  - From left to right: Esteban Millan Lozano, Sr., Esteban, Jr., Ricky and Rufo (father and three sons). These men come from Peru and spend several months out of each year to help Pachy Burns raise and tend sheep. Senior and Junior typically spend the most time in Montana. Pachy met them through an agricultural office in Wyoming. Pachy developed a great deal of respect for their expertise, patience and commitment. Base camp, near Greenough, Montana. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 86)
  - Esteban, Jr. keeping watch on sheep. This year's camp was set up across the road from "Paws Up" Ranch in Greenough, Montana. Pens were built in and around the tent in the background. The log structure was more than a hundred years old, but not used specifically for lambing, etc. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 87)
  - Esteban, Jr, and his younger brother, Rufo, examining a sick sheep. A couple hundred yards from the base camp, and a few miles north of Greenough, Montana. The buildings and camper beyond them line up near the road that leads to Greenough. Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 88)
  - Esteban, Jr. and Ricky dragging a sick sheep back to the base camp a couple hundred yards away. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 89)
  - Esteban Millan Lozano, Jr., near the base camp for lambing--a few miles from Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005. (Box 29, Image 90)
  - Bluesette Campbell, and her older sister, Piney Hardiman--daughters of Pachy Burns--out on the property of their father Daniel "Papa D" Larsen. This area is called Scotch Coulee, and has scattered remnants of what was once a vital mining town. They found a broken cup. October, 2013--the other side of the mountain, from Deer Lodge to their father's is about 8-10 miles. (Box 29, Image 91)
  - Bluesette Campbell and Piney Hardiman, daughters of Pachy Burns, having a laugh at an old broken cup they found on their father's property, not far from Red Lodge, Montana. We were visiting their father in October, 2013 (Daniel Lyle Larsen). I found this photograph, and the one which precedes it, to be a nice companion to the tape recorded interviews made during the preceding days with Piney, Bluesette, Jenn Nelson and Dan Larsen. Over the mountain from Red Lodge, Montana--an area called Scotch Coulee. (Box 29, Image 92)
  - Daniel Lyle Larsen, father to Piney Hardiman and Bluesette Campbell, and first husband of Judith Faye "Pachy" Burns. "Papa D" a the girls call him, is standing next to his rocket launching apparatus. The following year he will get a permit ot send one of his rockets 6-8 thousand feet into the atmosphere. He is 1/4 Potowatomi Indian. Dan's cabin, just over the hill from Red Lodge, Montana in an area called Scotch Coulee. October, 2013. (Box 29, Image 93)
  - Daniel L. Larsen, "Papa D," and his daughter Piney Hardiman near the end of an afternoon visit in October, 2013. Piney, Bluesette and I went up to his cabin/property just over the hill from Red Lodge, Montana. This area where Dan lives is called Scotch Coulee and is an old mining historical site. Bluesette is in the distance... we had been searching the ground for old relics, rusted items, kitchen utensils, etc. left behind by mining families. (Box 29, Image 94)
  - Piney and Jenn's home, Red Lodge, Montana. Piney Hardiman, Jenn Nelson (originally from Searsport, Maine) and Bluesette Campbell (who lives with her husband and two children in Meadow Lake, Saskatchewan, Canada, where they raise cattle). Red Lodge, Montana--October, 2013. (Box 29, Image 95)
  - Bluesette Campbell on her father's property during our visit in October, 2013. Near Red Lodge, Montana (Scotch Coulee). (Box 29, Image 96)
  - Judith Faye "Pachy" Burns looking into the mobile sheep shearing unit to make sure her sheep were doing okay while being sheared. Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2005 (late April). Made with a plastic Holga Camera. (Box 29, Image 97)
- Other Images, 2006-2007, 1 folder; 2 prints
  Two prints that are not related to other series in this collection.
  - Looking west, under the Mississippi River Bridge, Memphis, Tennessee. After a rare snowstorm. Holga plastic "panoramic" camera, 2006 February (6x20 inch print) (Box 27)
  - The godhead statue from behind (god the father, son, holy ghost). Salt Lake City, Utah, August 2007 (Box 27)
    Photograph made with Chatterley's 1st handmade camera, a 5x7 aluminium camera painted red.
- Publications and Interviews, 2004, 2008, 1 box
  Access Restrictions
  Original audiovisual recordings are closed to use. Listening copies are available.
  Consists of a publication on Asian migrant communities in N.C. containing Chatterley's work on Cambodian Americans, and five audio cassette tapes with interviews of Chatterley discussing his career as a documentary photographer. The interviews have been digitized and stored on a library server; listening copies must be made for access. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use this material.
  - Barbara Lau, From Cambodia to Greensboro: Tracing the Journeys of New North Carolinians. [Exhibit catalogue] With contributions by Thomas A. Tweed and Sally Peterson, and photographs by Cedric N. Chatterley, Greensboro Historical Museum, 2004 (Box 27)
    The Greensboro Historical Museum mounted an exhibition from December 2003 to December 2005 entitled From Cambodia to Greensboro: Tracing the Journeys of New North Carolinians. 2003 marked the twentieth anniversary of the Cambodian community in Greensboro, North Carolina, and the exhibition and book traced the community's growth and the experiences of its population.
  - Interview: Cedric Chatterley, Tape 1 of 2, 2008 April 18 (Box 27)
  - Interview: Cedric Chatterley, Tape 2 of 2, 2008 April 18 (Box 27)
  - Interview: Cedric Chatterley, 2008 April 20 (Box 27)
  - Interview: Lesley Williams/Cedric Chatterley, 2008 April 22 (Box 27)
  - Interview: Lesley Williams/Cedric Chatterley, 2008 April 23 (Box 27)